A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial records, Ann C. Whitman, Gubernatorial, Series 35 FA374
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller gubernatorial records, Ann C. Whitman, Gubernatorial, Series 35
1966-1973
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ronan, William J. (William John)
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich)
Boyd, Joseph H.
Morrow, Hugh
New York (State). State Commission for Human Rights
Whitman, Ann
New York (State). Dept. of Civil Service
New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller)
Cannon, James M.
FA374
23 Box(es)
Biographical/Historical note
Nelson A. Rockefeller served as governor of New York from January 1, 1959, to December 18, 1973. He was the first person elected to four consecutive four-year terms as a state governor.
File Plan note
Former Classification: III 15 35
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research, except where particular restrictions are noted.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Arrangement note
There are four subseries in this series, all of which are arranged alphabetically:
Subseries 1: Correspondence, 1967-1970 Subseries 2: Kissinger Reports on World Affairs and Countries, 1967-1969 Subseries 3: Issues and People, 1966-1973 Subseries 4: Campaign 1968
Biographical/Historical note
Ann Cook Whitman (1908-1991) was born in Perry, Ohio. She attended Antioch College, where she enrolled in the school's work-study program. She was sent to the Institute for Child Guidance in New York City. She chose a career as a secretary and left college. Her next job was as a personal secretary to Adele Rosenwald Levy, whose father, Julius Rosenwald, was a founder of Sears, Roebuck & Company.
In the early 1950s, Whitman worked for the Committee for a Free Europe. She was recruited to work for the Eisenhower presidential campaign in 1952, going on to work for Eisenhower as his personal secretary through his eight years in the White House and then for a short time at President Eisenhower's retirement home at Gettysburg.
In 1961, Whitman went to work for George Hinman, a political advisor to Governor Nelson Rockefeller. In 1965 she became Rockefeller's executive assistant. She went on to serve as Rockefeller's chief of staff during the first six months of his Vice Presidential tenure. In June 1975, Whitman returned to New York, assisting Rockefeller until her retirement in 1977.
Scope and Contents note
NOTE TO RESEARCHERS
This series contains the office files of Ann C. Whitman. They document her official activities in the execution of her duties as a member of Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller's staff. The actions, decisions, and exchanges of information or points of view documented here occured in the course of proposing and implementing policies for the Rockefeller administration, political campaigns, and/or Rockefeller's personal activities. However, unless a document is personally signed by Nelson A. Rockefeller, or is referred to in a document personally signed by him, it should not be assumed he saw the document or was aware of its existence or substance. Furthermore, researchers should bear in mind that staff files may contain documents or drafts addressed to Rockefeller that were never shown to him.
SCOPE AND CONTENT
In her role as Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller's executive assistant, Ann Whitman maintained a large number of his office files. This series primarily covers the time period surrounding the 1968 Presidential election, when Governor Rockefeller sought the Republican party's presidential nomination. A significant portion of the material deals with the deepening conflict in Vietnam.
Other Finding Aids note
Detailed finding aids for each series of this collection are available:
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Appointments Office (FA353)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Assembly and Senate Memos (FA354)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Joseph H. Boyd (FA355)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, James Cannon (FA356)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Affirmative Action (N. Lee Cook) (FA357)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Counsel's Office (FA358)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York State Committee to Reelect the President (FA359)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Jerry A. Danzig (FA360)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Executive Chamber (FA361)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, 55th Street (FA362)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Issue Books (FA363)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Arthur Massolo (FA364)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Hugh Morrow (FA242)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Office (FA365)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Civil Service Resolutions (Charles H. Palmer) (FA366)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Political Files (FA367)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Press Office (FA368)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Public Relations (FA369)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Departmental Reports (FA370)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, William J. Ronan (FA371)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Speeches (FA372)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Diane Van Wie (FA373)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, Gene Wyckoff (FA375)
Nelson A. Rockefeller Gubernatorial Records, New York Republican State Fund Raising Reports (FA376)
Latin America; International relations -- United States; International relations; International economic relations; Human rights; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; Affirmative action programs -- New York (State); Arms control; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Political science; Political campaigns -- United States; New York (State); New York (N.Y.); Legislation -- New York (State); Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; United States; State governments -- United States; Public relations; Public policy; Civil service; Civil defense -- United States; Civil defense; Arms control -- United States; Government policy; Federal government -- United States; Economics; Civil service -- New York (State); Vice-Presidents -- United States; Ronan, William J. (William John); Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich); Boyd, Joseph H.; Morrow, Hugh; New York (State). State Commission for Human Rights; Whitman, Ann; New York (State). Dept. of Civil Service; Republican Party (U.S.: 1854- ); New York (State). Governor (1959-1973: Rockefeller); Cannon, James M.
- Correspondence, 1967-1970; 1; 4 Document Box(es)
  Scope and Contents note
  This subseries consists of name and subject files containing correspondence between Governor Rockefeller and staff members and advisors. For example, a folder titled "Nixon-Agnew Campaign," contains information on Governor Rockefeller's role in the 1968 campaign of Richard Nixon. The information in this subseries deals with political and governmental issues and is primarily concerned with the 1968 presidential campaign.
  - Alfange, Dean (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Sends NAR suggestion for Vietnam resolution, support for president.
  - Appel, Dr. Kenneth (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Offers "My Dreams of Programs for our Country."
  - Auspitz, Josiah Lee and Thomas E. Petri (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Issues strategy for NAR, proposing NAR's comments stress unification behind "new themes for the last third of the century."
  - Board of Economic Advisors (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Memorandum from Alton G. Marshall with a framework for an economic advisory board for the state budgetary process.
  - Boe, Nils A. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Note of thanks to NAR from Boe, in his capacity as Director of the Office of Intergovernmental Relations, on suggestions from NAR to President Nixon on federal government issues.
  - Borella, Victor, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Advice on labor issues.
  - Braun, Ted (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Presidential issues and campaign suggestions from the Business and Public Relations Consultants.
  - Brydges, Earl (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Correspondence with the New York State Senator on plan to bring a Chrysler Corporation plant to the Buffalo area.
  - Campaign Reports (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Final reports from Rockefeller for President groups and other groups supporting NAR for President.
  - Cannon, Jim (Box 1, Folder 10)
    Press release announcing the selection of James Cannon as a Special Assistant to the Governor.
  - Catholic Report on Odyssey House (Box 1, Folder 11)
    Memorandum on a plan for assistance to rehabilitation center.
  - "Congressional Quarterly" (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Copy of article that proposes a Rockefeller-Reagan Republican ticket in 1968.
  - Danzig, Jerry A. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    Letter from Danzig to Ted Braun concerning television stations and air time around the country.
  - Department of Health (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Memorandum and press releases regarding actions of the New York State Health Department.
  - Diamond, Henry (Box 1, Folder 15)
    Memorandum regarding NAR's pending invitations and how to approach scheduling NAR's appearances.
  - Douglass, Robert (Box 1, Folder 16)
    1968 presidential campaign memoranda and press releases; report, "Reflections on International Cooperation for Latin American Development."
  - East-West Trade (Box 1, Folder 17)
    Report on issues regarding trade between eastern and western Europe.
  - Economic Aid Policy (Box 1, Folder 18)
    Report on issues regarding United States Economic Aid to other countries.
  - Economy, National (Box 1, Folder 19)
    Rockefeller for President press release of NAR statement on international economic policy; Winthrop Rockefeller speech to New York City economic group.
  - Electoral Process (Box 1, Folder 20)
    Memorandum concerning proposed change in the electoral process and its possible impact on the 1968 presidential election.
  - European Economic Community (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Overview of the Common Market, with focus on accomplishments and unresolved problems.
  - Foreign Intelligence Advisory Board (Box 1, Folder 22)
    Correspondence and memoranda regarding meetings of the board, of which NAR was a member.
  - Foreign Policy Article (Box 1, Folder 23)
    Reprint of NAR article, "Policy and the People," published in the January 1968 issue of "Foreign Affairs." Letter from Bill Moyers congratulating NAR on article.
  - Free, Lloyd (Box 1, Folder 24)
    Memorandum on polls conducted and information gleaned by Free.
  - Friele, Berent (Box 1, Folder 25)
    Correspondence and memoranda regarding a meeting between NAR and representatives of Brazil.
  - Gaud, William S. (Box 2, Folder 26)
    Report on Gaud, Administrator of the Agency for International Development.
  - Goldwater, Senator Barry (Box 2, Folder 27)
    Copies of clippings regarding NAR's endorsement of the Goldwater-Miller ticket in 1964.
  - Goodell, Charles E. (Box 2, Folder 28)
    Correspondence, memoranda, and press release regarding Goodell's selection to replace Robert F. Kennedy in the United States Senate.
  - Governor's Club (Box 2, Folder 29)
    Alphabetical list of members.
  - Greenbaum, Edward S. (Box 2, Folder 30)
    "New York Times" Op-Ed article by Greenbaum, a New York Attorney, on needed reforms of the judicial system.
  - Hall, Len (Box 2, Folder 31)
    Memorandum on the timing involved in a release of a poll on Ronald Reagan and the impact on the nomination of Richard Nixon.
  - Hanks, Nancy (Box 2, Folder 32)
    Memorandum from Hanks on the layout of briefing books.
  - Hinman, George (Box 2, Folder 33)
    Political memoranda on issues and NAR's image around the country.
  - Hughes, Emmett (Box 2, Folder 34)
    Memoranda with suggested positions and talking points on issues in the 1968 presidential campaign.
  - Javits, Jacob K. (Box 2, Folder 35)
    Memorandum from James Hellsmuth in repsonse to a request by Senator Javits to put several staff on the New York State Committee payroll and submit bills for payment; counter suggestion is for the committee to donate a sum to Javits' reelection campaign.
  - Javits, Marion (Box 2, Folder 36)
    Letter to NAR regarding a proposed art project.
  - Jones, Nina (Box 2, Folder 37)
    Memoranda to the Governor on Westchester political issues.
  - Kampmann, Mrs. Ike (Flo) (Box 2, Folder 38)
    Telegram from NAR congratulating her on appointment and introduction to the Inter-American Commission of Women.
  - Kennedy, Edward (Box 2, Folder 39)
    Correspondence from Senator Kennedy asking for NAR's participation in an oral hisotry project on Robert Kennedy.
  - Lazarus, Ralph (Box 2, Folder 40)
    Position paper from Lazarus, chairman of Federated Department Stores, on "The Crisis of Community and Urban Goals."
  - Lefkowitz, Louis (Box 2, Folder 41)
    Suggested remarks from the New York State Attorney General on consumer protection issues.
  - Levy, Gus (Box 2, Folder 42)
    Correspondence regarding NAR's belief that Levy was working for Nixon.
  - Lindsay, John V. (Box 2, Folder 43)
    Memoranda and correspondence concerning New York State-New York City issues.
  - Lockwood, John E. (Box 2, Folder 44)
    Political memoranda.
  - Logue, Edward (Box 2, Folder 45)
    Memorandum to Harry Albright with a biographical sketch of Logue, who was later appointed to head the Urban Development Corporation.
  - Lubell, Sam (Box 2, Folder 46)
    Political reports and polls sent to NAR.
  - Marshall, Alton G. (Box 2, Folder 47)
    Memoranda and draft press releases on New York State issues.
  - Massolo, Art (Box 2, Folder 48)
    Correspondence and memoranda concerning the archiving of the records of the 1966 gubernatorial campaign.
  - Melady, Thomas Patrick (Box 2, Folder 49)
    Memorandum to George Hinman from Melady, of the National Bipartisan Movement.
  - Miller, William E. (Box 2, Folder 50)
    Memorandum on delegate totals for the prospective 1968 presidential candidates.
  - Molitor, Graham T. T. (empty folder) (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Moore, Charlie (Box 3, Folder 52)
    Political information and polls; report, "The Conservative Apparatus and the 1968 Republican Nomination."
  - Moore, Tom (Speakers Bureau) (Box 3, Folder 53)
    Printed statements of NAR on various issues.
  - Morrow, Hugh (Box 3, Folder 54)
    Memoranda to the Governor from Morrow on political questions.
  - Morton, Thurston (Box 3, Folder 55)
    "New York Times" article, "Morton Sees GOP and United States at Brink."
  - Nathan, Richard (Box 3, Folder 56)
    Position papers and briefing material submitted to NAR.
  - Nixon-Agnew Campaign (Box 3, Folder 57)
    Correspondence, memoranda regarding NAR's support of the Nixon-Agnew ticket in 1968; press release/joint statement by NAR and Nixon pleading cooperation.
  - Peabody, Endicott (Box 3, Folder 58)
    Memorandum from the Massachusetts Governor, asking NAR to consider a draft as Hubert Humphrey's running mate.
  - Perkins, Roswell B. (Box 3, Folder 59)
    Memorandum to NAR on the cost of Social Security Proposals as proposed by the New York State Commission of Social Security.
  - Pfeiffer, Bill (Box 3, Folder 60)
    Memorandum to the Governor detailing a conversation between Harry Albright and Bill Pfeiffer; Pfeiffer feels NAR should urge Attorney Lefkowitz to run for another term.
  - Political (Box 3, Folder 61)
    General folder of political information; lists of New York State county committees; memoranda, correspondence.
  - President Richard M. Nixon (Box 3, Folder 62)
    Exchange of correspondence between Nixon and NAR on federal government plans and their effects on New York State.
  - Price, Robert (Box 3, Folder 63)
    Sends clippings regarding United States Congressman Ogden Reid.
  - Rhodes, Governor James A. (Box 3, Folder 64)
    Memorandum stating that Governor Rhodes feels NAR is "greatest governor in New York history" and most qualified to be president.
  - Robinson, Jackie, 1967-1968 (Box 3, Folder 65)
    Correspondence and memoranda from Robinson, offering continued support to NAR.
  - Rockefeller, David (CLOSED FOLDER) (Box 3, Folder 66)
    Conditions Governing Access note
    Restricted material
  - Rockefeller, John D. 3rd (Box 3, Folder 67)
    Sends letter from Chester Bowles on India situation.
  - Rockefeller, Laurance S. (Box 3, Folder 68)
    Memorandum on Eastern Airlines.
  - Ruebhausen, Oscar M. (Box 3, Folder 69)
    Memoranda on education and other domestic issues.
  - Snyder, Marty (Box 3, Folder 70)
    Letter to NAR from Snyder, serving as a consultant to the New York State Department of Mental Hygiene.
  - "Telephone" (Box 4, Folder 71)
    Daily lists of individuals to call or records of calls and brief subject line regarding calls that were received.
  - Thayer, Walter (empty folder) (Box 4, Folder 72)
  - Wells, Jack (Box 4, Folder 73)
    Memoranda and report on New York City politics, the 1966 gubernatorial race, and the 1970 mayoral campaign.
  - Whitney, C. V. (Box 4, Folder 74)
    Sends copy of "Lexington (Kentucky) Herald" editorial on NAR decision to enter presidential race.
- Kissinger Reports on World Affairs and Countries, 1967-1969; 2; 7 Document Box(es)
  This subseries contains reports organized, drafted, and written by Kissinger or his staff, and submitted to Governor Rockefeller by Henry Kissinger. Kissinger and Rockefeller worked together on projects dating from the time when Kissinger directed the Rockefeller Brothers Fund Special Studies Project. Kissinger was on the faculty of Harvard University when these reports were prepared. Following the 1968 presidential election he began his service to the federal government as a Special Assistant to Richard Nixon.
  The majority of the information contained in the reports and workbooks was eventually placed into the "Workbook on Problems in Foreign Policy of the United States," a staff report for the Republican Governor's Association Policy Committee, published in June 1968. There are also meeting notes with background information on foreign dignitaries that Rockefeller was scheduled to meet. There is also a folder of material prepared for Governor Rockefeller in advance of the Presidential Mission to Latin America, which was undertaken at the request of President Nixon in 1969.
  - Africa (Box 4, Folder 75)
  - Asia (Box 4, Folder 76)
  - Australia (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - Austria (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Belgium (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Britain (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Canada (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Common Market (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Czechoslovakia (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Defense (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Economy (Box 4, Folder 85)
  - Ecuador (Box 4, Folder 86)
  - Europe (Box 4, Folder 87)
    Related Archival Materials note
    See also separate countries
  - Fact Sheets, Questions and Answers, Recommended Postions (Box 5, Folder 88)
  - Fact Sheets, Questions and Answers, Recommended Postions (Box 5, Folder 89)
  - Foreign Aid (Box 5, Folder 90)
  - France (Box 5, Folder 91)
  - Germany (West) (Box 5, Folder 92)
  - Germany (West) (Box 5, Folder 93)
  - Government Organization (Box 6, Folder 94)
  - Greece (Box 6, Folder 95)
  - Iran (Box 6, Folder 96)
  - Italy (Box 6, Folder 97)
  - Kahn Notes (Hudson Institute) (Box 6, Folder 98)
  - Kahn Notes (Hudson Institute) (Box 6, Folder 99)
  - Kahn Notes (Hudson Institute) (Box 6, Folder 100)
  - Kahn Notes (Hudson Institute) (Box 6, Folder 101)
  - Korea (Pueblo Incident) (Box 7, Folder 102)
  - Latin America (Box 7, Folder 103)
  - Latin America (Box 7, Folder 104)
  - Latin America (Box 7, Folder 105)
  - Latin America - Latin American Mission, 1969 (Box 7, Folder 106)
  - Middle East (Box 7, Folder 107)
  - Netherlands (Box 7, Folder 108)
  - Norway (Box 7, Folder 109)
  - "Pending and Miscellaneous" (Box 7, Folder 110)
    Folder of miscellaneous policy material. Contains information about anti-ballistic missiles; general foreign policy, Vietnam, and a scheduled meeting with President-elect Nixon.
  - "Pending and Miscellaneous" (Box 7, Folder 111)
  - Position Books (Domestic) (Box 8, Folder 112)
  - Position Books (Foreign), 2 copies (Box 8, Folder 113)
  - Questions and Answers (Box 8, Folder 114)
  - Questions and Answers (Box 8, Folder 115)
  - Recommended Postions (Box 8, Folder 116)
  - "Red China" (Box 8, Folder 117)
  - Rumania (Box 8, Folder 118)
  - Russia (Box 8, Folder 119)
  - Schlesinger (Box 8, Folder 120)
    Meeting notes for scheduled appointment with Arthur Schlesinger, Jr. on the Cold War.
  - Singapore (Box 8, Folder 121)
  - Sweden (Box 8, Folder 122)
  - Taiwan (Box 8, Folder 123)
  - Thailand (Box 8, Folder 124)
  - Transcript (Box 8, Folder 125)
    Transcript of "Issues and Answers" program aired on October 6, 1968, with Secretary of State Dean Rusk discussing Vietnam.
  - United Nations (Box 8, Folder 126)
  - Vietnam (Box 8, Folder 127)
  - Workbooks (Box 8, Folder 128)
    Proposed Topics: East-West Trade; Economic Aid Policy
  - Workbooks (Box 8, Folder 129)
    Germany; United Nations
  - Workbooks (Box 8, Folder 130)
    North Atlantic Treaty Organization; European Economic Community; Germany; Berlin
  - Workbooks (Box 9, Folder 131)
    France; East-West Trade; Balance of Payments; Foreign Trade
  - Workbooks (Box 9, Folder 132)
    Non-Proliferation Treaty
  - Workbooks (Box 9, Folder 133)
    US-USSR Relations; Defense; Middle East; United Nations
  - Workbook on Problems in Foreign Policy of the United States - Volume I, 2 copies (Box 9, Folder 134)
  - Workbook on Problems in Foreign Policy of the United States - Volume II, 2 copies (Box 10, Folder 135)
  - Workbook on Problems in Foreign Policy of the United States - Volume II, Section 2, 2 copies (Box 10, Folder 136)
  - Workbook on Problems in Foreign Policy of the United States - Volume III, 2 copies (Box 11, Folder 137)
- Issues and People, 1966-1973; 3; 10 Document Box(es)
  This subseries contains a portion of the working files of Governor Rockefeller. New York State issues predominate; however, many files are concerned with national matters, reflecting his pursuit of the Republican presidential nomination in 1968 and his general interest in broader issues. On March 21, 1968, Governor Rockefeller declared he would not be a candidate for President in 1968. On April 30, he reversed himself and redeclared his candidacy for the Republican nomination. He actively campaigned until the Republican Convention. Of note in this subseries are three folders of Governor Rockefeller's handwritten notes from meetings he attended; the notes are undated and the majority do not identify the nature of the meetings.
  - Announcements (Box 11, Folder 138)
    Copies of press releases, including March 21, 1968 statement of non-candidacy and June 6, 1968 statement on the assassination of Robert F. Kennedy.
  - Answer Desk, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 139)
    Memoranda concerning the functions of the Answer Desk, run by Graham Molitor, monitoring candidate positions.
  - Arden House, 1968 (Box 11, Folder 140)
    Statements, press releases, and report of the Steering Committee of the Arden House Conference on Public Welfare Report.
  - Balance of Payments, no date (Box 11, Folder 141)
    Report on United States Balance of Payments to other nations and key issues.
  - Battery Park City, 1968-1969 (Box 11, Folder 142)
    Status reports, memoranda, plans and maps, and press releases on the plan to develop a portion of lower Manhattan.
  - Biography (Box 11, Folder 143)